Hello and welcome to our lecture on continuous
analog computing. So there's a lot of things
I want to show you. They don't matter too much
because the real overall theme here is continuous
means that these are devices that have sort
of knobs or gears or sliders that use physical
movement to approximate a computation. The key to
these devices like this device we'll play with in
a little bit is the carefully printed scales that
are on these devices. Because as you move them,
you are reading from the scales. You're inputting
data into them using the scales and you're taking
data out of them using the scales. And so that's
a critical element of these is that the scales are
very very carefully calibrated and built. But then
once you've got those scales, the device is pretty
simple to operate. That's the basic idea. Now,
the oldest known continuous analog computer is
the Antikythera mechanism, and it was found in
a shipwreck in uh around Greece near an island
called Antikythera. And it uses gears to model the
known solar system. It can model the sun and the
moon and the earth, Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter,
and Saturn. And it doesn't just think of it as
uh 24 hours a day, 365 days a year. That actually
is a just a simplification. And that's why we have
leap years that it can model the more complex
cycles like 19 year cycles and a 76 year cycle
and a 223 cycle when this is a lot of people want
to think of this thing as quite mystical like
like holy mackerel people built a computer this
long ago and they it turns out it's not that all
complex but it's it had this idea of such an early
such a precise device so much data from solar star
and planet observation that went into this that
it really has this air of mystery and mysticism
about it. And this led to a movie called Indiana
Jones and the Dial of Destiny. And the basic idea
was is that in addition to the 247 year cycle,
there's an even longer cycle. And at some point,
this dial of destiny, which is an anti mechanism,
will predict when a time portal will open and
close. So, you can go back in time sort of for one
24-hour period, and that's pretty fun. And I love
the movie, and I I love the anti mechanism.
They've made replicas of the anti museum
uh mechanism in various um museums. But here's the
interesting thing. They're not very mystical at
all because you can buy one on Amazon. And I did.
So here is a cheap imitation anti-ra mechanism and
you can see here that it has gears and it has
very careful scales right it's got these scales
for both the sun scale and the moon scale so
that the phases of the moon you know whether
it's a full moon a new moon etc and so the idea is
is and these the sizes of these gears is carefully
calculated by the data in the solar system and
when you spin it around. There we go. You can see
that the gears are keeping everything in control
and you can then stop and then read. So, we're
now in the middle of summer and it's a particular
day and the moon is in a particular spot. And so,
that is a very simple anti mechanism. Now,
ironically, the way I'm holding this, um, we have
this simple notion that we were taught in school
about the solar system that it's just flat plane
like this and all of the um, all the planets are
kind of in a one plane. But it's not true because
it just turns out that the whole sun is moving.
So, it's like the sun is moving through the the
the Milky Way and all. I don't know if I got that
very well, but there you go. The sun is moving
through the Milky Way. So, you can I couldn't
get licensing for a really good video of this,
but there are some really pretty videos called you
can go search or look for AI like tell me about
the actual motion of the Earth through the Milky
Way galaxy. Oh, and by the way, the notion that
the sun was the thing around which everything
was rotating, the helioentrism got Nicholas
Copernicus in trouble in 1543. and you can Google
that as well. Now, I want to talk a little bit
about modern continuous analog devices. One's not
quite so modern. It's been replaced by the Hen
calculator, which is the slide rule. And the other
is an a wind calculator for airplane pilots that
uses a circular calculator to do trigonometry and
Pythagorean theorem, mostly to compensate for wind
direction on an airplane. We'll talk about both of
them. So, let's start talking about a slide rule.
So a slide rule is a device. Again, all analog
continuous devices have a scale on them. And
this is a really tiny, very fine, highly accurate
scale that maps numbers to their corresponding
logarithm. So you could think of this entire
device as a function mapping x to log x. And
then what you do is you move this back and forth
and you can effect doing addition and subtraction.
And then you can add logarithms. And that's the
same as multiplying and subtracting logarithms is
the same as dividing as long as you can keep track
of the exponent. And so if you go back in the 50s
and the 60s or if you watch the movie Hidden
Figures, you will see that everyone is carrying
around a slide rule. And when I watched that movie
Hidden Figures, I absolutely love that detail of
everyone having a slide rule because that's really
what it was like to be an engineer back in those
times because we didn't have hand calculators. All
we had was a slide rule to do our multiplication
for you. And I built an online slide rule that
you can play with. So the next thing I want to
talk about is computing wind correction in
an airplane. So if you take an airplane,
it spins a propeller and it it goes through the
sky at a certain speed and you can point it in any
direction you want and then you go up and you fly
for a while, point it wherever you want and then
you come back down. And if you know the distance
and you know the speed, you can figure out about
how long it's going to take an hour and 15 minutes
to get there. But there's a problem. There's wind.
So let's just say I want to fly this little
airplane from me to you. Let me grab it better.
I want to fly this airplane from me to you. So I
and and you're 100 miles awayish and it's going to
take me an hour to get to you. But what if there
is a wind that's coming from this direction? Okay.
So the problem is if I fly aim at you, the wind is
just going to push me and I'm not going to get to
you. And not only it'll take me more than an hour
because the wind is actually not just moving me
but slowing me down. So when that hour is done,
I will not be where you're at. I'll be lost.
And so a big part of teaching us pilots is to know
how to adjust what we call the crab angle, which
is to move to aim the airplane in a different
direction than we want to go to compensate for
the wind that's pushing us. If our airplane goes
100 knots, which is like roughly miles per hour,
and we want to go west 270° and the wind is
out of 300° at 15 knots, if we if we fly west,
the the wind will both slow us down. So, where
should we actually point the plane to actually
have a ground track that is west? And what is our
effective speed so we can calculate how long it's
going to take us to get there? Okay, so one way
to do this is the law of sines. Everybody knows
the law of sines. The law of sines says that
the ratio of the sign of an angle to the sign,
the length of the side opposite that angle
is the same for triangles, most triangles.
Turns out if the angles get too big or too small,
you've got to kind of transform a little bit. So,
it's not too easy. But you know there is math that
tells you how to calculate this effect of wind on
an airplane both in terms of changing ground speed
and a direction you have to go. And so you'll see
we have a headwind is the first one where the wind
is coming from our right and in front of us. Then
we have a side wind where it's just coming from
our right. And then we have a tailwind which is
coming from our right and behind us. And you have
to calculate all those things because your plane
may speed up or slow down and it might affect
where you have to point the plane. And I provide
there some simple beautiful mathematics in Python.
And it's actually more complex than that because
not every triangle works this way. And so you
have to adjust your triangle sometimes. So our
airplane goes west and we want to go 270°. The
wind is out of the northwest at 300° and 15 knots.
The answer is we're going to fly a heading of
274 degrees and calculate our distance based on
a westward ground speed of 87 knots. That's the
answer, which we could get through trigonometry.
But we really don't want to have pilots running
trigonometry in a plane. Maybe at night they
get a call on a radio and it says the wind is no
longer out of 300 at 15 knots. it's out of 243 at
80 knots or whatever. And you got to recalculate
where you're at because you're like you're, you
know, you've gone a certain distance. You got to
recalculate where you're going to point the plane,
all those things. And as as interesting as as
complex as the trigonometry is, we really don't
want uh pilots to be doing sign computations
in the in the darkness. And they won't and
they didn't have hand calculators. And so part of
the part of the reason that pilots still train on
this stuff is that we don't want to depend too
much on technology. I literally have on my cell
phone a a an application that can tell me where
the weather is, where I'm at, how high I am, how
fast I'm going, all the other planes in the sky,
etc. And and that's great, but part of piloting
is not depending on technology too much. you need
to be able to just fly the plane if somehow the
technology fails you. So, this is still taught in
pilot training. It's still tested in your pilot
exam. And it it it's an interesting thing and
the notion that this is something that came from
probably the 30s or the 40s. Um it's a really cool
analog computer that we learn today as pilots. So,
let me show you how this works. We're going to do
a simple calculation for airspeed correction and
heading correction on an E6B. Our problem is a 15
knot headwind. So, we put our little hole at 100
and then we go up 15 knots, 110, 115, and put a
mark right at the 15 knot mark. And the direction
the wind is coming from is 300°. We're flying
300°. we would have a headwind of of 15 knots
which would slow us down. Now our plane goes
100 knots so it' be going 85 on the ground but
that's not where we want to go. We don't want to
fly to 300. We want to fly to 270. Now as we're
moving this in a sense this analog calculator is
doing a bunch of sines and cosines and Pythagorean
theorem but we don't care we're just moving it.
It is a physical thing and it is recalculated.
So the first thing we do is we put the heading
that we intend to fly up there at the true index.
So we're going to fly 270 or westerly. Then what
we've got to do is we've got to take the point,
this point here. We got to move it down to 100
knots because that's how fast our plane is. And
you can see that the headwind is slowing us down.
So now we've compensated for the headwind. And so
if you look, our plane normally goes 100 knots,
but with this particular wind, this 15 knot wind,
it's going to do 86 87 knots. And we also have
to figure out what we call the crab angle,
which is the way we have to fly to go to the west
to compensate for the wind. So we have to add four
degrees. And that is 1 2 3 4. So now we have
with without doing any mathematics nothing but
manipulating a physical device. We have calculated
the actual air speed and the compensation that we
need to do for a wind of 15 knots out of a heading
of 300 in order to maintain a heading of 270. The
point of this is not to teach flying. It is to
the fact that a carefully engineered, carefully
calibrated physical analog device can do beautiful
calculations that are graphical in nature and
frankly very easy to use. Don't need a lot of
training. You just have to know how to rotate and
move and read using things like sliding, rotating
scales, gears. You can even do crazy calculations
with things like water and pulleys. So, this
kind of concludes our brief look at analog
computing devices. is up next. We're going to
talk about digital computing devices. And digital
computing devices are things that make clicking
noises. They're still physical devices. They're
by definition analog, but they have two states
and they are stable when in each of the states
and we can have input to change their state. So a
pen is kind of a classic physical digital device.